Today's דף Daf is ס"ד Samech Dalet 64. We pick up in
the middle of ס"ג עמוד ב' Samech Gimmel Amud Bet by the
צד"ת. Tsadat. We're dealing with different types of ריבית דרבנן, Ribbis D'Rabbanan,
particularly those that come in the context of sales and buying stuff
essentially futures, or not actually buying futures, buying stuff at today's prices
but delivery in the future and then to what degree that might
seem to be a type of a ריבית Ribbis when you get
more than you very more value than you paid for initially. The
גמרא Gemara picks up on the צד"ת Tsadat smack in the middle
of ס"ג עמוד ב'. Samech Gimmel Amud Bet. רבא ורב יוסף דאמרו
תרווייהו, Raba V'Rav Yosef De'Amru Tarvaihu, one starts with word תרווייהו. Tarvaihu.
רבא Raba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef they both say, האי מאן
דיהיב זוזי אטרא חריפא. Hai Man De'Yahiv Zuzei Atara Charifa. Somebody who
gives money on the early market price, the early market price means
the market price for the early produce just as the stuff is
beginning to become ripened and come to market. Now apparently רש"י Rashi
says that that's when the prices are still low, which is interesting.
You know, I don't know, you figure like you know at the
height of the season is when the prices are cheaper because there's
more supply, here there's less supply. I don't exactly get it but
anyway apparently when the stuff is just coming to market, people, you
know the prices are still are like possibly the low. Maybe the
produce isn't as good? Maybe the produce isn't as good. So anyway,
but so you're allowed to buy at that price and again for
later delivery right, which is when the prices will be higher most
likely, but like some of the requirements we had yesterday got raised,
you know, remember the normal הלכה Halacha is it's when it's
יצא השער. Yatza HaSha'ar. יצא השער, Yatza HaSha'ar, which means that it's
now the meaning now like everybody is selling and the market price
has been established. That's not just as the stuff, you know that's
not the שער חריפא, Sha'ar Charifa, that's יצא השער Yatza HaSha'ar when
like everybody is now selling and the price has been established at
least for this period of time. And under those circumstances you can
buy either if you, you know, give the money now, you know,
give money now okay, and then you can buy even if he
doesn't have the fruit okay, or if he has the fruit even
if you're only paying with a loan, okay, even
if you're only paying with a
loan, okay, buying on credit fine better even no you're not buying
on credit. Is that the same thing?
That's a good question. I don't know. Maybe not because at least
when you're paying with a loan there's an element of קניין כסף.
Kinyan Kesef. When you're buying on credit there's no aspect of קניין
Kinyan that takes place. Okay, now we're going to have a case
about שער חריפא. Sha'ar Charifa. Okay, now again the point is is
that it has to be some element of the sale either there's
the money or there's the fruit. So שער חריפא, Sha'ar Charifa, it's
harder to be a sale because again since there's not that established
price, it's not like he can turn around part of the reason
here you can just give the money is because he can just
turn around and buy it from somebody else, right? Everybody is selling
there's an established price and so on. שער חריפא Sha'ar Charifa not
everybody is selling. So in order to do it for שער חריפא,
Sha'ar Charifa, it's only if any guesses? He has the fruit. Okay,
it is not enough to give him the money because he can't
he needs to have the fruit and give him the money. That's
a good question. Not sure about that. But it's certainly not enough
to give him the money because he can't just turn around and
buy it from somebody else.
Okay,
so האי מאן דיהיב זוזי אטרא חריפא. Hai Man De'Yahiv Zuzei Atara
Charifa. It's actually speaking about a case of actually giving the money.
וצריך לאתחזויי לבי דרי. V'Tzarich L'Itchazuye L'Be Dari. You have to appear,
present
yourself, התפעל Hitpa'el of חזי Chazi to see, make yourself seen, present
yourself, okay at the threshing floor. Okay, you have to go to
the guy where his fruit is and present yourself and do the
deal, okay, and say I'm paying you now for the based on
this early market price. After having already appeared to him to give
him the money to appear again? No, when you're giving the money
you have to appear to him. You can't do it, you can't
maybe do it in the marketplace, you can't maybe, you know, I
don't know what what another case case would be but send money
through through somebody else, anyway you have to show up there at
the at the threshing floor. למאי? L'mai? So it says for what
purpose? אי למקנא הלא קני, Ee L'Mikna Halo Kani, if it's to
actually take full possession you're not, you're not actually taking the fruit
into your possession right now you're only giving the money now. אי
לקבולי עליה מי שפרע, Ee L'Kabbule Lei Mi ShePara, if it's in
order that it should be at least rabbinically binding not you know
quasi-binding because you gave the money and now there would be a
מי שפרע Mi ShePara to back out and that's what enough makes
it like a sale that you're allowed to do this. So that's
true, אי לקבולי עליה מי שפרע, Ee L'Kabbule Lei Mi ShePara, כי
לא מתחזי נמי מקבל עליה מי שפרע. Ki Lo Mitchazi Nami Mekabbel
Lei Mi ShePara. As long as the money changed hands, okay you
would also get the מי שפרע. Mi ShePara. I mean why what's
this special הלכה Halacha of appearing at the threshing floor? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, לעולם לקבולי עליה מי שפרע. Le'Olam L'Kabbule Lei
Mi ShePara. Fine, you're not taking possession of the fruit, it's one
of these standard sales for future delivery where you're not actually taking
possession right now, so it's only the מי שפרע Mi ShePara level.
And nevertheless, והאי מאן דיהיב זוזי אטרא חריפא V'Hai Man De'Yahiv Zuzei
Atara Charifa when you're buying the stuff at the early market price,
דבי תרי תלתא יהיב. De'Be Trei Tlasa Yahiv. So therefore you actually
do deals with a couple of people. of different farmers because maybe
as Micah was saying, you know, since it's just the early produce,
it's not yet clear who's gonna have the best produce, what the
quality is gonna be, so basically what you're gonna do is you're
gonna enter into a deal with a couple of farmers you're trying
to חאפ chap the good low price, okay, but you're not yet
sure about the quality of the produce, so you're going to enter
into a couple of deals. And maybe what you're hoping to do
is back out of those deals once you see what the quality
is, okay, so any so therefore if that's true any particular farmer
feels like alright this is more like a promise, it's not binding
yet cause he's doing this deal with a couple of people, right?
So therefore to make it binding, the גמרא Gemara is going to
say you have to really show your serious commitment to the deal.
Otherwise even if money changes hands and normally that's enough, in this
context it's not enough because every farmer's expecting that you might in
the end not go through with it. Why would he give me
מי שפרע? Mi Shepara? They're expecting you not to show. So maybe
you wouldn't get a מי שפרע. Mi Shepara. That's what part of
what's up. In order to get the מי שפרע Mi Shepara you
have to show up because otherwise the context is is that you're
not fully committing even even maybe if you're giving money because you're
just in the end it's understood that you're playing the market, okay?
So יוי, yoy, so אי לא מיתחזי ei lo mitchaze if you
don't appear, לא סמכא ליה דעתיה. lo samcha lei daatei. He doesn't
really rely on it, there's no real commitment yet to the deal
because he knows you're doing this deal with a couple of people,
okay? ולא... V'lo... I'm sorry, אי מיתחזי
ליה ei mitchaze lei I'm sorry I skipped a line, thank you.
אי מיתחזי ליה סמכא דעתיה. ei mitchaze lei samcha daatei. Then if
you show he relies on you, ואי לא v'ei lo and if
you don't show up אמר ליה amar lei אמינא amina so he
can say back to you look I assumed דאשתכח פירי דשפיר מדידי
de-ishtachach piri di-shappir mi-didi if you're going to find some farmer that
has better fruit ושקלית v'shaklit you would go ahead and take it
from that guy so therefore I wasn't really fully committed to the
deal, okay? I didn't think you were fully committed to the deal,
I wasn't fully committed to the deal, okay? So in this context
in order for the money to be at least this binding to
the degree of the מי שפרע Mi Shepara which then makes this
whole thing acceptable from a ריבית ribbis perspective, okay, you have to
actually show up, otherwise the context is people aren't really entering into
a deal yet. Did the buyer back out also? Yes, presumably exactly
that's what the סמכא דעתיה. samcha daatei. אמר רב אשי Amar Rav
Ashi הא דאמרת ha-de-amarta משום מסמך דעתא mishum mis'mach daata now that
you say the reason for appearing is that only in that context
does he really trust that this is going to go through so
therefore אפילו אשכחיה בשוקא ואמר ליה סמכא דעתיה. afilu ashkechei b'shuka v'amar
lei samcha daatei. Even if you did it in the marketplace and
not showed up but you said to him
explicitly I'm going to do this deal with you and you can
rely on me, I am going to go through with it with
you, I am not playing the game and considering my other options,
so in that type of a case that would be sufficient, there's
no magic of showing up, it's creating a context where he knows
you're not just giving to a couple of people and you're going
to just do the best one that presents itself, yes. If the
buyer gives the full price, does he... he gives money... It seems
like he gives the full price, right. So he might be giving
the full price to two or three different people. Yeah, it's a
good point, right. And then expect that he's going to be able
to just get his money back. And can the sellers back out
as well? Like a down payment or something like that or is
that... and then... Like a non-refundable?
Yeah, there's not a real way to do that within הלכה, halacha,
the way to do that would more be like a type of
a... like of a penalty clause which you have in contracts, if
you back out then this will be the penalty and then they
can sue, אסמכתא asmachta issues, right, exactly. But in this way it
does work two ways, if you can back out I can back
out so you know as long as we all understand the rules
of the game we all understand that it's not yet final. At
least for the sellers, just to show he had the food and
you had the money at least for this, right. At least that
was certainly the context yes. And the sellers also going to try
and
have with different buyers? They might, that's a good point, they might
be courting a couple of different buyers, that's a good point. אמר
רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so it's... it's sort of like you
know my kids are in this stage of life about like you
know the colleges and the early decision and whatever, everybody is trying
to get the best deal and maximize your options before committing, right,
that's a good point. Okay, אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman כללא
דריבית, klala d'ribbis, okay, here's a very important line, the general principle
of... of determining if something is ריבית, ribbis, obviously you can't just
read this line and forget about the rest of the פרק, perek,
but one general test case is כל אגר נטר ליה, kol agar
natar lei, a שכר s'char for being a שומר, shomer, meaning here
is extra money in order so that I don't have to pay
up right away, okay? So that's basically what ריבית ribbis is, you
give me the loan and then I give you some extra some
money so that I can wait. Now that's classic ריבית, ribbis, you
give me a hundred I give you back a hundred and ten.
But it also could be in rabbinic ריבית ribbis in the context
of a sale, you give me the money and I don't give
you the product until later and because you are letting me deliver
the product later, actually I am giving you more product for your
money, okay? So that would be the type of rabbinic ריבית, ribbis,
alright. So... And that wouldn't be a problem like did you say
let's say I mean I don't know if we'll call sometimes the
line between a penalty clause and interest is very slim, like in
others let's say a penalty clause you don't... the loan is due
this but if you don't pay me back then you just get
charged ten dollars more, if you pay back on time I'm not
going to charge you anything more, or like a discount. Okay, so
we'll see some of that. Okay, so some... so those are the
types of cases we'll be dealing with exactly those. What happens if
if... here's the price, the price is a hundred but if you
pay me
early... at the gas station. One price for cash, one price for
credit. What's what's the price for credit saying? If you want to
wait to pay me, you'll have to pay me more. Right, that's
what the credit price No, it's because they actually get I know,
they get charged by the they get charged by the credit card
company. I know, but let's pretend that that was the case. Okay.
Really a false path. Exactly. There is a thing about like buy
buy this sofa with our financing. Oh right. Yeah. And then pay
more. Right. Okay. Right. All right, so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, כל אגר נטר ליה אסור. kol agar natar
lei asur. ואמר רב נחמן, ve-amar Rav Nachman, says רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, האי מאן דיהיב זוזי לקירא. hai man de-yahiv zuzei le-kira. Now
here we're going to get an example of this idea of of
letting me wait to pay and therefore I'm going to give you
more.
Okay, האי מאן דיהיב זוזי לקירא. hai man de-yahiv zuzei le-kira. Somebody
is is giving money for wax. דאזלי ארבע ארבע. de-azli arba arba.
Wax. Okay, דאזלי ארבע ארבע. de-azli arba arba. They were going for
whatever units of wax per זוז, zuz, per dollar. ואמר
ליה ve-amar lei יהיבנא לך ה' ה'. yahivna lach he-he. And the
seller comes and says to you, you know what? I will give
you five units of wax for a dollar. Okay, but I'll deliver
it later, I'll deliver it in a week or tomorrow. It's a
question of how much later is later. Okay, but I'll deliver it
in a week. Okay, but I'm going to give it to you
for five. So because he is waiting to deliver, he's going to
give me more for my money. Okay, so here's the issue. Here's
the way of testing. אית ניה גביה שרי. it nei gabbei shari.
If he actually has the wax in his store, okay, and maybe
he has to go back to his store and he won't get
back to his store for two days and come back to, you
know, maybe he's in the market and his store is a day
away, but as long as he has access to it and he
owns it, then it's like it's like a sale and it's not
like רבית. ribbis. It's not like he's real, you know, he's getting
you know, like he's giving me extra because he needs he's able
to hold on to it without yet producing. He has the thing,
he can give it in theory, he just doesn't have immediate access
to it. So therefore it's a sale and it's okay. לית ניה
גביה, let nei gabbei, if he doesn't have it and he has
to go ahead now and produce it or use the money to
buy it or something like that, right, in that case, לית ניה
גביה, let nei gabbei, so אסור, asur, it's forbidden. And if you
think about it, that's also like a classic loan, right? Why would
I be borrowing money from you if I had the money myself?
Now maybe I have assets but I don't want to liquidate them
or I have the money but I want to use it for
something else, right, you know, but like if I really had the
access to that money myself, I wouldn't be borrowing. So the fact
that I'm taking it and I don't have the ability, the access
to that money to pay you back and I need to only,
you know, change the circumstances in order to, again, that's what sort
of makes it more like a loan and I'm giving you some
benefit in order so that you can give me that extra time
in order so that I can wait to pay you back. Okay,
so that's the general principle. And we're going to see so the
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. pshita. Now the גמרא Gemara says obvious because
this is actually going to be a משנה mishna later on about
this case, about that if I have to wait till my son
comes and brings me the key to my to the office so
that I can get into there and get you your stuff, that's
okay because I still own it, okay, even though I don't have
it right now, even if the delivery is going to be later.
And even in that case I can actually give you more for
your money. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, isn't that an
obvious application of a law that we know? No,
לא צריכא דאית ליה אשראי במתא. lo tzericha de-it lei ashrai be-masa.
I am a wax seller and I deal do business with like
other wax sellers or other wax producers and people owe me money,
owe me wax. There are wax producers in the city that I
that that they owe me wax. So I sell you wax, I
don't have any in my possession, but I do have people who
owe me wax. Is that considered to be like I have it
in my possession and I just have to get it, or is
it not yet in my possession? אשראי ashrai means credit. Yeah. So
I have credit with other wax sellers, they owe me wax. Okay.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. So anyway, מהו דתימא, mahu de-teima, I might think,
כיון דאית ליה אשראי במתא כעד שיבא בני או עד שאמצא מפתח
דמי, ke-it lei ashrai be-masa ke-ad she-yavo beni o ad she-imtza maftayach
dami, that's the phrase that we're going to see later on. Since
they owe me the wax, it's like a case of where I
own it and I just have to wait for my son to
come or I have to wait to get the key and it's
just not immediately in access, but fundamentally I own it and therefore
it's okay to give you extra. So
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, it's teaching us that because it's
lacking being
collected, כמאן דלית ניה דמי. ke-man de-let nei dami. It's like you
don't have it. Which is true, you know, you never know when
you're actually going to be collecting from your from your debtors and
how accessible that is. Okay. So here the הלכה halacha is that
in the context of a sale, if you actually give the person
more for his money because of delayed delivery, that is like רבית
ribbis in the cases where you did not have the product. Okay?
If you had the product but it wasn't immediately accessible, it's okay.
But if you didn't have the product, then that is like a
case of רבית. ribbis. All right. Then why can't you say the
same thing for a loan? You know, let's say I borrow a
hundred dollars but I actually have the hundred dollars with me, but
whatever, you know, then maybe I can get better terms. Okay, but
you know what? Because this is only רבית דרבנן. ribbis derabbanan. Okay.
A loan, if it's real רבית, ribbis, it's real רבית. ribbis. It
doesn't those conditions don't matter. Okay, this is those characteristics that make
it look enough like gave you more money than you have to
give back. Okay, האי מאן דאוזי פיתי מחפרי. Hai man d'ozi piti
me-chafrai. Now this is just a teaching of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
doesn't have much to do with ריבית. ribbis. It's actually a little
ironic. It's going to be a case where the lender gave you
more money than you have to give back. Okay, האי מאן דאוזי
פיתי מחפרי. Hai man d'ozi piti me-chafrai. You borrowed money from your
friend. פיתי? Piti? Like money. פיתי, Piti, like, yeah, like זוזי. Zuzi.
Okay, it's
Aramaic for... okay, so, you found more. Michael, let me $100. Sure,
Dove. Here you go. Did you count it? No, you counted it,
whatever. You counted out $100, he gave me five $20s and then
I went ahead and I took it home and I said, wait,
wait, there's six $20s here. Okay, so אי בכדי שידעת נושא, I
b'che-dei she-daas notay, if it is something that was reasonable that he
made a mistake with, like he miscounted, he gave me six $20s
instead of
five, מחייב לאהדורי ליה, mechayev l'ahadorei lei, then I have to return
it to him. ואי לאו, V'ee lav, and if it's not, if
I counted it and there was five $20s and there was, I
don't know, a five stuck in the middle. Okay, so presumably, like,
you know, you wouldn't have confused... lost count, and you wouldn't have,
like, not seen it. So what's it doing there? So ואי לאו
מתנה בעלמא הוא דיהיב ליה, V'ee lav matanah b'alma hu d'yahiv lei,
so he's just given me a little gift. He knows, look, I'm
hard up, I need more money, especially if you think that a
classic example of borrowing money is for poor people who don't have
enough to sustain themselves. I don't know if that's the Gemara's assuming
that. Okay, you know, that's why the Torah doesn't let you charge
interest is because, you know, it's not dealing with commercial context. So
therefore, Michael here feels bad for me. He knows, you know, I'm
trying to keep my dignity, I'm not asking for a handout, I'm
asking for a loan, but he'd like to help me out a
little bit. So therefore, what he does is sticks in an extra
five into the, you know, into the wad. Okay, so it's clearly
would not have happened by mistake, so he's just giving me a
gift. Next time stick in a hundred, okay Michael? So מתנה בעלמא
הוא דיהיב ליה. matanah b'alma hu d'yahiv lei. So I only have
to pay him back a hundred, I don't have to pay him
back
105. Okay, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's
the... היכי דמי בכדי שידעת נושא? Heichi dami b'che-dei she-daas notay? Well,
what's an example of this? אמר רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף, Amar
Rav Acha b'rei d'Rav Yosef, בעשיריותא ובחמשייתא. b'asiiruta u've-chamshaita. If it's like
tens and fives. So that's why, like, if Michael counted out $20s
and there was an extra $20, or he counted out tens and
there was an extra ten. But if he was counting out $20s
and there was an extra five there, especially if you think that
the coins... and my example of dollar bills aren't so great because,
you know, they could get stuck together or whatever. But if you
think about coins of different metals and different sizes, you know, you're
not going to make a mistake if you're giving me gold דינרי,
Dinarei, you know, you would see a silver דינרא Dinara that was
there. So that's not seen as a mistake. Okay, so now if
you look at
Tosafot, Tosafot says... Tosafot says: בעשיריותא ובחמשייתא. B'asiiruta u've-chamshaita. Tosafot says: המה
היו רגילים בחמישה כדרך שאנו מונים אחד אחד ולדידן הוי בכל ענין
בכדי שידעת נושא. Heima hayu regilim b'chamisha k'derech she-anu monim echad echad
u'l-didan havei b'chol inyan b'che-dei she-daas notay. So
Tosafot says the Torah... so Tosafot says the whole thing is a
moot point because, you know, nowadays any mistake we would make in
counting would be a mistake. It's hard to imagine a case where
the guy we could assume the guy would have, you know, wouldn't
have been a mistake and he would have intentionally included the extra
amount. Okay, but anyways, if there were a scenario... now the Gemara
is... but the Gemara imagines a case that that could be. So
now the Gemara continues. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי,
Amar lei Rav Acha b'rei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi, ואי אינש תקיפא הוא,
V'ee inish takifa hu, דלא יהיב מתנה, d'lo yahiv matanah, מאי? mai?
Let's say Michael is this nasty guy who's never done anybody a
favor in his life. Okay? So how could I assume that the
extra five dollar bill is a מתנה, matanah, you know? He would
never do anybody a favor. So
אמר ליה, Amar lei, דילמא מגזל גזליה ואבליה בחשבון. Dilma migzal gazlei
v'avlei b'cheshbon. Ah, there's other explanations why Michael's giving me five bucks.
Maybe he stole five bucks from me and he's embarrassed to admit
it, so he's hiding it back in the hundred dollars that he's
lending me. Look. So exactly.
דתניא, D'tanya, הגוזל את חברו והבליע לו בחשבון. Ha-gozel es chaveiro v'hivlia
lo b'cheshbon. You steal from me and then you you absorb it,
you hide it back in other money that you're giving me, יצא,
yatza, he fulfills his obligation of returning the money. So now the
Gemara says: ואי אינש דאתי מעלמא, V'ee inish d'asi mei-alma, דלא שקיל
וטרי בהדיה. d'lo shakil v'tari bahadei. If this guy is some stranger
I never met him before in my life, דלא שקיל וטרי בהדיה,
d'lo shakil v'tari bahadei, I've never had business with him, he's from
a neighboring town, there's no possibility he would A, do me a
favor or B, ever stole any money from me. מה? Mah? How
could you explain that? אמר ליה, Amar lei, דילמא אינש אחרינא גזליה.
Dilma inish achreina gazlei. You know what? Because maybe Dove over here
stole from me and Dove doesn't... and feels that the best way
to get the money back for me is to use Michael as
his as his cut-out, okay? To use Michael as the way. And...
so אמר ליה, Amar lei, כי יוזיף פלוני פיתי מינך. Ki yozif
ploni piti minach. So Dove there says to Michael: you know what?
When the other Dove... I shouldn't have given the example of Dove.
David says to Michael: when Dove borrows money from you, I know
he's going to come to you for money, when he borrows money
from you, do me a favor, הבליה ליה בחשבון, havlei lei b'cheshbon,
stick in this five dollars into it. Okay, so anyway, we come
up with some scenario, which is so fascinating. You would think that
the more likely scenario would be that it was a mistake. So
it's so fascinating that we just you know if we if it's
not reasonably you know if there's a reason to think it's not
a mistake or if there's whatever good reason to think it's not
a mistake, we're going to assume that it was intentional. It's quite
fascinating. Okay. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, I really don't know
what to do with that, like what the logic is behind it.
You would think the presumption would be that any... The extra money
is clear like why don't I at least clarify it with him
you know? So the proof of like the desire to try to
define it as a מתנה matana when I'm getting money from somebody
else you know it's just strange. Anyway so does that ever really
say הלכה halacha that like you know someone gives in a case
where it's אין הדעת טועה ein hadaat toeh you know in a
case where
it's not likely that this was a normal mistake you know? So
but you know but then the question is yeah but you would
so I understand that when it really isn't likely that it was
a mistake but then you would look at the context and try
to assume bigger picture right not just by the which is what
the גמרא Gemara does and the גמרא Gemara tries to push back
even given weird contexts you're just going to assume it's a מתנה
matana and not a mistake. All right let's go on. Okay. I
was thinking yes this clarification you would bring up the same embarrassment.
Yeah I was wondering about that. Maybe the clarification then he would
have to say it was a mistake even if it wasn't because
then you would force him to come forward. So maybe that was
just the reality at that time that people would do that sometimes.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says maybe it's the reality now. Okay
so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב כהנא Amar Rav Kahana
says Rav Kahana הוינא יתיבנא בשילי פירקי דרב Havina yasivna beshilei pirkei
de'Rav I was I came at the end of Rav's שיעור shiur
okay I came
late ושמעית דקאמר קרי קרי veshamis deka'amar kari kari and I heard
that Rav was saying gourds gourds he's talking about this gourd and
you do a gourd and you do a gourd and whatever all
I could get that's all I could pick up for the שיעור
shiur that's what you get when you come at the last five
minutes okay ולא ידענא מאי קאמר Velo yadana mai ka'amar and I
didn't know what he was talking about what's all this about gourds
I had no context I didn't know what was going on okay
מאי קאמר Mai ka'amar but בתר דקם רב batar dekam Rav after
Rav got up left the שיעור shiur okay אמרי להו amri lehu
I said to the Rabbis who were gathered
there מאי קרי קרי דקאמר רב mai kari kari deka'amar Rav what
was all this discussion about gourds that Rav was talking about אמרו
לי Amru li they said to me הכי קאמר רב hachi ka'amar
Rav this is what Rav says האי מאן דיהיב זוזי לגינא hai
man deyahiv zuzei legina somebody goes to a gardener okay אקרי akari
for gourds okay so I'm going to buy gourds there are gourds
now growing in your garden they have yet to be picked דקאזלי
עשרה קרי בני זרתא Deka'azli asara kari benei zarta okay and now
and there are you know going like ten gourds for
a זרתא zarta a זרתא zarta right it's
it's like a hand stretch like this from your thumb to your
pinky it's like two טפחים tfachim okay which is basically a half
of an אמה ama okay so it's a half of a foot
let's say okay so I you bought ten gourds that are growing
in your garden okay and they are currently a half-foot long these
gourds okay ואמר ליה יהיבנא לך בני גרמידא Va'amar lei yahivna lach
benei garmida and basically I gave him ten dollars for the ten
gourds but he said to me I will pay you ten gourds
that are an אמה ama long that are foot-long gourds okay איתנהו
isht'hu now if those gourds are present שרי shari then it's permissible
because then it's like I actually bought the gourds I'm sorry איתנהו
isht'hu excuse me if he has ten gourds that are foot-long the
price right now
is ten dollar for let's say a dollar whatever a dollar for
ten half-foot gourds and he's willing to sell me a dollar for
ten foot-long gourds if he actually has the foot-long gourds then שרי
shari it's permissible he can sell things at whatever price he wants
to ליתנהו leisnhu if he doesn't have the foot-long gourds so then
it's forbidden אסור assur because again I'm paying him and he's going
to deliver it later he's not delivering it now he's going to
deliver it later and he's going to deliver it later and he's
going to give me stuff that's twice as big so that's classic
ריבית ribbis wouldn't it be the same gourds no that's what they
grow that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to get to okay
if it's the same gourds that grow but if we bracket that
for a moment okay it's now going ten half-longs for a dollar
and I buy ten foot-longs for a dollar okay so if he
actually has them and he's just giving me a discount gezuntheit if
he doesn't have them then he's giving me a bonus extra for
waiting time and that's the problem why isn't this אונאה onaah because
it's a שער חריפא shaar charifa oh yeah I mean let's assume
that everybody knows the price and you know if you know what
the price is and you give discounts or whatever you're allowed to
so גמרא Gemara says פשיטא peshita it's obvious no מהו דתימא mahu
deteima like Michael said this is not just the case of you
know giving extra amount later כיון דממילא קרבו kivan demimmela karbu the
gourds are
these same gourds are going to grow in a month to be
foot-long gourds so he's actually going to deliver the same gourds if
I would have actually purchased them right now with a קנין סודר
kinyan sudar I can't do משיכה meshicha I'd pull them out of
the ground but if I do some קנין kinyan right now then
they would be my gourds that had grown to be a foot
long so okay I'm not right now just giving the money I'm
not fully purchasing them but maybe it's acceptable for him to just
let them grow naturally and deliver them later when they're bigger maybe
that's not like ריבית ribbis because it's my own I don't yet
own it but it's sort of like it's the thing that I
bought that just naturally grew okay if you bought it at the
half-foot price but if you bought it at the foot-long price right
then I could just give you these same gourds yeah sure yeah
but it's still like a דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba
laolam you don't know really how something's going to right it's not
really a דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba laolam because they're
there they're in the ground if something happens to the gourds let's
make this clear you don't yet own them. If something happens to
them and he doesn't have the gourds to deliver, he has to
give you your money back. He can't say, 'Oh, your gourds got,
you know, destroyed in the drought.' You don't own them yet. Okay,
so that's part of what makes this whole thing problematic. Okay, so
okay, פשיטא. peshita. No, מה דמקיים ממילא קא רבו, ma d'mkayam m'meila
ka rabu, they're going to grow on their own, שפיר דמי, shafir
dami, it might be good. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, it's
not. כמאן? k'man? Okay, כמאן, k'man, who is this going like that's
not good? כי האי תנא דתניא, ki hai tana d'tanya, like the
following תנא tana that taught: הולך לחלוב את עזיו, holeich lachlov et
azav, you're going to milk your goats, ולגזוז את רחליו, v'ligzoz et
rachelv, and to shear your sheep, ולרדות את כוורתו, v'lirdot et kavarto,
and to take the wax out, the honey out of your, out
of your beehive.
מצאו חבירו, matsa'o chaveiro, you found your friend, and you say to
your friend, אמר לו, amar lo, מה שעזי חולבת מכור לך, ma
she'izi cholevet machur lach, I will sell you right now for $100
however much I get out of my, out of my goats, okay?
I don't know how much it's going to go, maybe normally we
would assume a normal, you normally get $120 worth, but who knows,
maybe it'll be $90 worth. I'll tell you what, buy sight unseen
$100 however much I milk it's yours, okay?
מה שרחלי גוזזת מכור לך, ma sheracheli gozezet machur lach, whatever my
sheep does I'll sell you sight unseen, you'll take a risk but
it's going to be at a discounted price based on what it
normally would be let's say, it's sold to you. מה שכוורתי
רודה מכור לך, ma shekavarti roda machur lach, מותר. mutar. All these
cases permissible. You're selling him the full amount, it's sight unseen, he's
taking a risk, is it more likely you're giving him a discount
of what the price normally would be? The normal assumption would be
it would be worth 100 and I'm going to sell it to
you for 90. Fine, but it's not like any, no, I and
I'm not going to deliver it right away, it's going to take
me a month to shear all my sheep or whatever, or two
days, or who knows what. So is it a problem that I
am delivering it to you later? Right, this is the problem. I'm
delivering, I'm selling it to you for 90, my guess is it
would come to $100 worth, I'm selling it to you 90 and
I'm going to deliver it to you later, and if it actually
is what it normally would be worth, you would get $100 of
product for your $90 with a later delivery. So the answer is
it's permissible. Why is it permissible? 'Cause for all we know it's
going to be worth $80, so because you're taking a risk, you're
not necessarily getting more product, okay, even though there's a good chance
you'll benefit out of it, it's okay. All right, you got it?
Yeah, this is like a CSA model like when when,
yeah, it's a good point, it's a good point. You buy into
a farm for $500 and you don't know how many tomatoes, often
you get more for your money, but you might get less for
your money, right, okay. So okay, so the גמרא Gemara says שפיר
דמי. shafir dami. So wait a minute, okay. מכור לך מה שכוורתי
רודה לך מכור לך מותר. machur lach ma shekavarti roda lach machur
lach mutar.
That's okay. אבל אם אמר לו, aval im amar lo, מה שעזי
חולבת כך וכך מכור לך. ma she'izi cholevet kach v'kach machur lach.
If you say to him, what I'm going to do, wait, let
me just check רש"י. Rashi.
Okay, if you say to him I will sell you, I'm going
to go milk my cows and I will pre-sell you a specific
amount, 100 gallons, and I'm going to sell them to you at
a discounted price, okay, so then that's the classic case where it's
אסור. assur. You're selling him a specific amount, right, and he's going
to get a full 100 gallons' worth which is normally worth $100
and you're selling it to him for 90 because he's paying you
now for later delivery. That's not allowed. Okay, that's again a case
where you get the money now, later delivery, and therefore you get,
you give him more than that money would normally buy him. Okay,
so מה ש, ma she, where was, אבל אמר מה שעזי חולבת
כך וכך מכור לך, aval amar ma she'izi cholevet kach v'kach machur
lach, מה שרחלי גוזזת כך וכך מכור לך, ma sheracheli gozezet kach
v'kach machur lach, מה שכוורתי רודה כך וכך מכור לך, ma shekavarti
roda kach v'kach machur lach, in all those cases I'm going to
give it to you when I actually milk and shear and whatever,
and I will, I will sell you X amount at a discounted
price, אסור, assur, that's forbidden. And that's the end of the ברייתא.
braita. ואף על גב דממילא קא רבו, v'af al gav d'mmeila ka
rabu, who is now the גמרא? Gemara? Exactly. So exactly as you
point out here, now we're switching to Aramaic, so now the גמרא's
Gemara commenting on this, ואף על גב דממילא קא רבו. v'af al
gav d'mmeila ka rabu. Now wait one minute. This is like the
gourd case, because in the case let's say of the milk or
of the wool, it's just going to continue to grow. So
and nevertheless it's a problem. Right, what if we said right now
that the wool on the sheep is worth $90, but the 100
units is worth 90 on the sheep, but by the time it,
you know, it, what do you call it? You know, it, it's
delivered, that amount is going to grow and be worth $100. So
and nevertheless it's a problem even though it's the same thing that's
growing. So you see this idea of a lower price for later
delivery, even if it is actually the thing that is growing and
that's what's causing the increase of product, nevertheless it's not acceptable. All
right, you see the parallel? Now the גמרא's Gemara going to say
it's not an exact parallel. ואף על גב דממילא קא רבו, v'af
al gav d'mmeila ka rabu, wait, wait, let's finish this. כיון דליתנהו
בההיא שעתא, keivan d'leitnhu b'hahi sha'ata, since that extra wool and that
extra milk or whatever is not present at that time, אסור, assur,
it's forbidden. So therefore that's parallel to your case about the gourds.
ואיכא דאמרי, v'ika d'amri, some say אמר רבא, amar Rava, no. כיון
דממילא קא רבו, kivan de-mimeila ka rabu, שפיר דמי. shapir dami. If
the gourd will grow naturally, it's okay, even though you don't own
the gourd like now, you're paying the money for the gourd now,
it's quasi like you own it, and the gourd itself is just
growing, so it's not like I'm actually giving the guy extra product
for his money. I'm just giving him the product that he bought
or tech—he didn't totally buy, the product he paid for that has
now increased. That actually is okay to deliver foot-long gourds even though
he paid for them when they were half-long. How is that different
than our case about the sheep and the milk? So the גמרא
Gemara says, והתניא כהאי גוונא אסור. ve-hatanya ke-hai gavna assur. What about
this case about when you pay so much amount of wool or
whatever it's forbidden, even though that wool that's going to grow from
what it is right now? הגמרא Ha-Gemara says no, התם, hasam, לאו
מיניה קא רבו. lav minei ka-rabu. There,
it is not the thing itself that is growing, okay? דשקיל ליה
להאי ואתי אחריני בדוכתיה. de-shakil lei le-hai ve-asi achrinei be-duchtei.
If you were to shear the sheep, more hair would still grow.
It's not the current hair that is growing, right? Some hair's already
getting longer but it's growing from the animal, right? If you were
to shear the hair, more hair would grow. If you were to
milk the cow now, more milk would come. If you were to
take out the honey, more honey would be made. So it's not
that the thing that is bought is increasing. It's stuff that's being
added onto the thing that is bought, right? If I buy all
the milk in your cow's udder right now and we wait a
week—I mean, I know you gotta milk it regularly, maybe that's not
a good example. I buy all the honey in your beehive right
now and we wait a week, there's going to be more honey
in the hive, but the honey didn't grow. Honey was added to
the hive. If I buy all the hair on your sheep right
now, there's going to be more hair, wool, in a week, but
the hair didn't grow, more hair came out. And therefore, when you
give that to me, you're giving me something new and extra for
a wait, for delayed delivery. Whereas when you give, I buy the,
pay for the gourd, and you give me a bigger gourd, if
you were to have taken the gourd out of the ground, nothing
more would have come after it was taken out of the ground.
So it's the gourd itself that grew and you're just giving me
what I bought. Okay, הכא, hacha, here, מיניה קא רבו, minei ka-rabu,
the gourd itself grew from itself. דכי שקיל ליה להאי, de-chi shakil
lei le-hai, once you take the gourd out of the ground, לא
אתי אחריני
בדוכתיה, lo asi achrinei be-duchtei, no other gourd is going to come
in its place. So again, part of what makes this acceptable is
that when you pay money, this is why, you know, איזהו נשך
Eizehu Neshech had to follow הזהב, Ha-Zahav, because in הזהב Ha-Zahav we
learned that even though the sale isn't final until you do משיכה,
meshichah, there's a quasi sale when you pay the money. So since
you paid the money, you sort of like own the gourd now—not
really, but you sort of do—and therefore if the gourd itself grows,
it's not like you're getting something new for delayed delivery. Whereas in
the case of the wool or the milk or whatever, it's not
the wool itself that grew and it's not the milk itself that
grew and therefore you are getting something extra for delayed delivery and
it's not good. Right, and that's why the gourd case is מותר
mutar and these cases, the milk and the honey, is אסור. assur.
Exactly. Exactly. So if so, if so,
since it's like that quasi sale when some money has been exchanged
for the gourd, yeah, so then why is—I'm the buyer. In the
meantime, delivery is in three weeks. The gourd is almost a foot
long, right, and then there's a blight. Right. How come it's not
my problem? I quasi—it's mine. Because you only quasi bought it, you
didn't really buy it. That's what I wanted to know. Right. Very—that's
why you can back out. It's only strong enough for a מי
שפרע Mi Shepara and to make this not really a case of
ריבית. ribbis. Okay, so it's strong enough not to make it ריבית,
ribbis, it's strong enough to obligate the seller unless—no, he can back
out if he wants to get a מי שפרע. Mi Shepara.
That's what it means, like a non-binding sale. I know, but no
one wants to get a מי שפרע. Mi Shepara. Okay, but תוספות
Tosafot also discusses that in cases where there's a real loss you
don't even get a מי שפרע. Mi Shepara. מי שפרע Mi Shepara
is more like you just arbitrarily want to back out. If you
have good cause, you don't even get a
מי שפרע. Mi Shepara. Okay, in context—for instance, airlines buy fuel right,
in huge contracts in the future, and then the fuel price goes
up. Right. Change—the fuel, there is fifty thousand gallons of gas somewhere
on which they bought a contract, but then the price either went
up or dropped down and they're still—they're still
bound by their—their guaranteed delivery. Exactly, exactly, exactly, it's a perfect example.
Okay, so it'd be familiar? Yep, totally. So now let's see the
next case in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay now, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
so אביי Abaye says, שרי ליה לאיניש למימר ליה לחבריה, shari lei
le-inish le-meimar lei le-chavrei, you can say to your friend, היי לך
ארבעה זוזי אכביתא דחמרא, hei lach arba'ah zuzei a-chavisa de-chamra, here's four
זוזי zuzei for your barrel of wine. Now, here's the story though,
אתקפא, itakfa, if before delivery the wine turns into vinegar, ברשותך, bi-rshusach,
then you're going to have to deal with that, then the sale's
בטל batel or you're going to have to give me different wine.
Okay, that's your problem. יקרא וזילא, yakra ve-zila, but if it goes
up or down, if there's just a fluctuation in market prices, ברשותי,
bi-rshusi, then that's fine, I bought the wine and I'll deal with
the fluctuation in market prices. But if it spoils before delivery, then
you gotta give me other wine. Okay, so now, אמר ליה רב
שרביא לאביי, amar lei Rav Sharvya le-Abaye, so רב שרביא Rav Sharvya
said to אביי, Abaye, is this a type of... Is this a
type of a ריבית Ribbis case? Because look what happens. I gave
you four dollars. You're going to deliver it in a week. You
have the wine, okay, but there is a slight possibility that I'll
lose out. I'll get wine less than I value for. But in
basically because you're suffering the cases of it turning into vinegar, there's
more likelihood that if there's any loss or whatever you'll suffer and
that you know so is it's not exactly ריבית Ribbis because I'm
not promised to get something extra, okay, but the way it's like
ריבית Ribbis is that I'm to a certain degree protecting my principal
and going to be entitled know that I'm that there's a good
chance I might get increased value if the price goes up. So
so
it's not exactly easy to see why this should be a problem,
but let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. He
says then האי קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד הוא. Hai karov l'schar v'rachok
l'hefsed hu.
This is a case where you the buyer are more likely to
make money and it's more less likely for you to lose money.
You would lose money if the market prices fluctuates and goes down,
but you would make money if they went up. There are three
scenarios: it turned to vinegar or it changed in market prices. Two
of those three scenarios the seller
loses. I'm sorry, two of those three scenarios the seller loses. If
it is if it turns to vinegar the seller loses and if
it goes up the seller loses. You only lose in one of
those scenarios where the market price fluctuates down. So since this deal
you're much more likely to get money out of it, to get
you know better value out of it than you paid, should that
be like ריבית? Ribbis? All right, which seems very strange, you know,
because it's like there's not again it seems like there's once there's
a reasonable risk in either way even though it's favored in your
direction, why to consider it ריבית? Ribbis? Which is basically what the
answer is. אמר ליה כיון דמקבל עליה זולא קרוב לזה ולזה הוא.
Amar leh keivan d'mikabbal alei zula karov l'zeh u'l'zeh hu. Look, there
are cases where you lose money out of it. Okay, yes, the
seller will lose money in more cases than you will, okay, because
he's also taking the the responsibility of of it turning into vinegar
when you're not. Okay, but since based on market fluctuations if it
goes down you'll lose money, as long as it's the type of
a deal where there's a reasonable chance that you'll lose, you can't
consider it ריבית Ribbis if it works out that you gained. Okay,
yes. Just on the those probabilities if the probability of the wine
decreasing in market price is greater, let's suppose there's a seventy percent
chance the price is going to go down and a thirty percent
chance that the wine's going to increase in value,
then even if I add in the probability that the wine turns
to vinegar and it's not my price, that could just even it
out. It's still just yeah. But the גמרא Gemara is making a
bigger חידוש. Chidush. The גמרא Gemara is saying it might be that
seventy percent of the time you the person who gave the money
are going to come out ahead in this deal, okay, but nevertheless
since thirty percent of the time you're going to lose money, you
right, or it'll you'll break even or whatever, but whatever in cases
where you're not breaking even seventy percent you're gaining and thirty percent
you're losing. Thirty percent you losing is enough that it's a that
it's a business deal and it's not a ריבית Ribbis deal. Now
the question is what would be the percentages? Because what we're dealing
with is a concept that is called קרוב לשכר ורחוק להפסד Karov
l'schar v'rachok l'hefsed could be a type of a ריבית, Ribbis, but
how קרוב לשכר Karov l'schar and how רחוק להפסד Rachok l'hefsed does
it have to be? Right? If I make a deal with you
I'm going to give you a hundred dollars, okay, if you know
you know if you know we're going to draw a random number
from one to a hundred, right, if it's one then you give
me only have to give me back ninety-nine dollars, any other number
you give me back a hundred and ten. Okay, so that looks
like ריבית, Ribbis, right? So yeah so that like that's really clarifying
because the difference here might also be like there's not just risk,
there's uncertainty. So like the difference between risk and uncertainty is like
the economic terms like the un it's not just that there's a
seventy or thirty percent chance, it's that I'm uncertain in actuality what
the future percentages will actually be. Oh you don't know what the
percent right. Whereas case is a lot more structured. You have no
uncertainty, you only have risk. Right, that's a good point, that's a
good point. So anyway so that's goes that's the issue which we'll
see more of this קרוב לשכר ורחוק. Karov l'schar v'rachok. But it's
an interesting point because I want to point out by the way
it's good to just clarify the issue before. It seemed like all
those cases before, you know, like when I gave you money and
then you were going to deliver me later and you were going
to deliver me based on today's prices or whatever, it seemed like
why was the גמרא Gemara so bothered with that? It might be
that later when you deliver it maybe the maybe the you know
the price will go down, maybe I'll lose money, maybe you'll deliver
you know maybe I mean no yeah maybe you'll lose money, you'll
deliver the hundred bushels and they'll be worth less. Why was the
גמרא Gemara so bothered that I'm giving you money now, you're delivering
it later and it's going to be worth more? Maybe it'll be
worth less. It sounded like those cases were that under
normal circumstances it was going to be worth more later and that's
what partly created those problems, right, that it was רחוק קרוב לשכר
ורחוק להפסד. Rachok karov l'schar v'rachok l'hefsed. If it was really just
a normal type of a risk, it was just as likely I'm
paying you today's prices, you're going to deliver it month in a
month from now, it's just as likely it'll be worth less than
it'll be worth more, right, you probably you probably So we probably
don't need as many of these requirements, right, because it's probably much
less like ריבית. ribbis. Have I lost everybody now, or you're with
me? Yeah. What were the facts of this case again? So the
facts were you bought wine and the guy was assuming the, who
was delivering the wine later, was assuming more risk than you were.
He was going to take the loss if it turned to vinegar.
He was assuming more risk than you were. Nevertheless, it's not like
ריבית ribbis because you're also assuming a certain amount of risk. Now
תוספות Tosfos by the way discusses is it only a problem if
you haven't yet fully taken possession of the wine or even after
you even if you did a קנין kinyun on the wine, but
you structured a deal? This gets to a question that was asked
before. Let's say you actually did a קנין kinyun on the wine
but you structured a deal that, okay, I'm being קונה koneh it
now, deliver it in a month from now, but if in a
month from now it turns to vinegar, then retroactively the sale is
בטל. batel. So it's totally a hundred percent of a קנין kinyun
but you structured it in a way that you would wind up
benefit, you know, protecting yourself from risk. Could it be that something
that was a hundred percent of a קנין kinyun but structured in
a way to ensure that you would get profit and protect yourself
from risk would still be a ריבית ribbis problem because it would
look like ריבית? ribbis? Okay, until now we've been dealing that you
haven't been קונה koneh yet. You paid money, so that's more, or
no, it was a quasi-sale but it was to be more like
a loan because you didn't fully take possession. תוספות Tosfos raises the
possibility here, he goes back and forth, that it could be that
even if you took possession of the wine and it was a
total sale but you structured it that in this condition retroactively it'll
be בטל, batel, so you protected yourself from risk and ensured that
you know, or increased the likelihood you'll get gain, that maybe even
that could look like ריבית ribbis and be a דרבנן derabbanan ריבית
ribbis problem. Right. But most likely we're dealing with a case that
you have not yet taken possession of the wine and therefore you
haven't taken possession, it's going to be delivered later, and in the
case where you are protecting yourself from risk and most likely going
to gain, is that a case of looking like ריבית ribbis or
do we say since you're exposing yourself to a certain amount of
reasonable risk actually it is not like ריבית? ribbis? And I just
wanted to point out that that parallels our discussion before about paying
money for the fruit at today's prices and getting delivery later, presumably
a major part of that reason that that was problematic was because
in their normal circumstances it was going to be worth more later
and that was a case of, you know, קרוב לשכר ורחוק מהפסד.
karov l'schar v'rachok m'hefsed. It is possible it would be worth less
later, but most likely it's going to be worth more.
Yeah. We're assuming as if the seller is taking on more risk
than the buyer. Right. But the question of turning to vinegar, isn't
that something that the seller would have awareness more awareness of, like
that's his business, right, to know how good... So that's what תוספות
Tosfos discusses. תוספות Tosfos says isn't a normal case of turning to
vinegar anyway like a מקח טעות mekach ta'us and other reasons that
it's not good and whatever, so תוספות Tosfos discusses that. So that's
a good question. It's a בבא בתרא Bava Basra discussion. Let's take
a look at the next משנה. Mishna. המלוה את חברו. Hamalveh es
chaveiro. Now, this comes a little bit easier. לא ידור בחצרו חנם.
lo yedur b'chatzeiro chinam. Now we get to questions of no deals.
You lent me a hundred dollars, I paid back a hundred dollars.
What are things that because you lent me the money you can't
now I can't do you any particular any like favor out of
the ordinary favors because those favors are going to be interpreted as
a type of a ריבית? ribbis? Okay, a type of, there was
no deal, you lent me a hundred dollars and then after you
lent me a hundred dollars you said, you know Dov, I'm going
to be in
Riverdale, you know, next week and I understand that you're going to
be away for שבת, Shabbos, can I stay in your house? And
I say,
remember I lent you a hundred dollars, even if you don't say
that, right? But like, you know, I let you stay in my
house for free, okay, after you lent me money, is that like
a type of a ריבית? ribbis? And that's ריבית מאוחרת, ribbis me'ucheres,
which means that there was no stipulation about it. Even though there's
no stipulation, because I am now, you know, giving you something in
the aftermath of you having lent me money, it becomes seen of
rabbinically of a type of a ריבית. ribbis. Okay? So המלוה את
חברו לא ידור בחצרו חנם, hamalveh es chaveiro lo yedur b'chatzeiro chinam,
you now cannot live in my field for free, in my house
for free. ולא ישכור הימנו בפחות v'lo yiscor mimenu b'pachos and you
can't rent from me at a discounted rate. After you lent me
a hundred dollars then you say, I'd like to rent your car,
I know it normally goes for fifty dollars a day, but I
think I'm going to, you know, I'd like to rent it for
forty dollars today. What do you think about that, Dov? Okay, or
maybe I can't even suggest it. We'll discuss in a minute who's
suggesting it. I can't say oh, you want to rent a car?
Fine. You know what, I normally charge fifty, but it's okay, you
can have it at forty. For you, forty. Okay, so anyway, ולא
ישכור הימנו בפחות מפני שהוא ריבית. v'lo yiscor mimenu b'pachos mipnei shehu
ribbis. Okay, because it's not literal ריבית, ribbis, but it's like ריבית,
ribbis, okay. Like the Ferrari from כתובות. Kesuvos. Exactly. Okay, now אמר
רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi
amar Rav Nachman אף על פי שאמרו. af al pi she'amru. הדר
בחצר חברו שלא מדעתו אינו צריך להעלות לו שכר. hadar b'chatzer chaveiro
shelo mida'ato eino tzarich l'haalos lo sachar. Anybody remember בבא קמא? Bava
Kamma? If you live in somebody's yard without his permission, you don't
have to pay him rent. You might remember that's the case of
זה נהנה וזה לא חסר ze neheneh v'ze lo chaser in a
situation where... where you normally wouldn't rent it out, so you're not
losing anything from it even though I'm gaining, I don't have to
pay you rent. Even though that's true, הלוהו ודר בחצרו, halvahu vedar
be'chatzero, if after I lent you money, you came and dwelt and
lived in my yard, okay, sorry, after you lent me money, excuse
me, you came and dwelt in my yard. So in that case,
you have to, yes, if you came and dwelt in my yard,
צריך להעלות לו שכר, tzarich le'haalot lo sachar, you have to pay
me rent. Because you lent me money, now you live in my
yard without paying me rent, even though normally I could not collect
for that, that's not something that actually, like, you know, I can
demand payment. So you say if I can't demand payment, then there's
no dollar value to you having gained that benefit. Right? You understand
the point? If you could come and do it and I couldn't
take you to court, so the fact that you're doing it, there
might be no dollar value, certainly no collectible dollar value, so maybe
you should be allowed to do it even though you lent me
money. No. In the context where you lent me money, it is
seen as a benefit that I've given you and therefore a type
of ריבית. ribit. Okay? צריך להעלות לו שכר tzarich le'haalot lo sachar
and if you want to live in my yard, you would have
to pay me rent. מאי קמ''ל? mai ka mashma lan? What does
that teach? דתנינא, detanyina, we've taught in a משנה: mishnah: המלווה את
חבירו לא ידור בחצרו חינם ולא ישכור ממנו בפחות מפני שהוא ריבית.
Hamalveh et chaveiro lo yadur be'chatzero chinam velo yiscor mimenu be'pachot mipnei
she'hu ribit. It's our משנה. mishnah. משנה mishnah says you can't live
for free in the guy's yard because it looks like ריבית. ribit.
Now, אי מהמתניתין, ei mehamatnitin, הוה אמינא, hava amina, הני מילי hanei
milei בחצר דקיימא לאגרא וגברא דעביד למיגר. be'chatzer dekayma le'agra ve'gavra de'avid
lemigar. I might have said that it's only in cases where living
in my yard would have been something I could have collected for,
okay, if you came and lived in my yard. Why? It would
be a case where A, you need to rent a house, so
you are נהנה neheneh from doing it, and B, my house is
on Airbnb, it's a standard rental, so I'm losing out by the
fact that you're in it. That's a case of זה נהנה וזה
חסר. zeh neheneh vezeh chaser. Because you're living, I'm losing out. And
that type of a case, you came and you lived in my
Airbnb house and prevented me lending it to somebody else, I can
collect rent from you in court. Okay, so maybe when our משנה
mishnah says you're not allowed to live for free, it's that type
of a scenario. A scenario that otherwise I would be able to
collect money from you in court, where you got a real dollar
value from that transaction. Okay? אבל בחצר דלא קיימא לאגרא, aval be'chatzer
dela kayma le'agra, if the yard is one that I normally do
not rent out, so it's a זה לא חסר. zeh lo chaser.
וגברא דלא עביד למיגר, ve'gavra dela avid lemigar, or it's a case
where you don't really even need a yard to live in, okay,
so it's really a case of זה לא נהנה. zeh lo neheneh.
אימא לא, eima lo, I might think in that case where I
cannot collect money from you in court if you came and did
it, maybe even after you lent me money you would be allowed
to because it's not like you got any real dollar value out
of it. קמ''ל ka mashma lan that no, you can't, because in
this context it looks like ריבית. ribit. איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, others
say: אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן אף על פי
שאמרו הדר בחצר חבירו שלא מדעתו אינו צריך להעלות לו שכר. Amar
Rav Yosef bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman, af al pi she'amru, hadar
be'chatzer chaveiro shelo mida'ato eino tzarich le'haalot lo sachar. That even though
when you sort of do it, you don't have to pay, so
it's not normally would be defined as a dollar value collectible in
court, this benefit. הלווני ודור בחצרי, halveni vedur be'chatzari, if I come
to you and I say, I say Jacob, lend me a hundred
dollars, and you know what, Jacob? Lend me a hundred dollars and
you can even stay in my house. I know you're going to
be in Riverdale for this week, you can stay in my house
this week, just lend me a hundred dollars. So in that type
of a case, צריך להעלות לו שכר. tzarich le'haalot lo sachar. He
would have to pay me rent. Okay, now obviously there's a big
difference. If I say it during the time that I'm borrowing money,
it makes it much less, oh, it's just some favor that I
did to him. No, it's much more ריבית-like ribit because I'm offering
him that favor at the time of the loan, okay? So מאן
דאמר הלוהו, man de'amar halvahu, that if you just borrowed money and
then later offered him a favor it would be אסור, assur, כל
שכן הלווני, kol sheken halveni, certainly if you offered him the favor
when you were proposing to borrow the money or asking to borrow
the money. ומאן דאמר הלווני, veman de'amar halveni, but if you say
it's a problem only when you offer the favor when you're borrowing
the money, אבל הלוהו aval halvahu no. But if when you go
ahead and you just סתם stam borrow and a week later you
offer him the favor or he, you know, then it's not a
problem. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? כיון דמעיקרא לאו אדעתא דהכי אוזפיה,
keivan de'meikara lav ada'ata de'hachi ozfih, since that was not implicit at
the time of the loan, at the borrowing the money, the lending
of the money, and then after you borrow the money, now you
just סתם stam want to do him a favor, he asks for
a favor, לית לן בה. leit lan bah. Then that's not considered
really a ריבית ribit problem, that's just like a favor. Okay, so
those are the two opinions. Now, תוספות Tosafot asks a great question.
תוספות, Tosafot, if you take a look at this תוספות, Tosafot, אבל
בחצר דלא קיימא לאגרא, aval be'chatzer dela kayma le'agra, תוספות Tosafot says
like this, תוספות Tosafot says: והשתא קשיא. ve'hashtah kashya. It's two lines
in from that תוספות Tosafot אבל. aval. כדמוכח רבה מיניה בשמעתא. kedemochach
Rabbah mineih beshmata. Okay? So he says like this. So תוספות Tosafot
says that we פוסקין pasken actually let's start from the beginning of
the תוספות. Tosafot. He says: כהאי לישנא קמא דאפילו הלוהו אסור קיימא
לן כדמוכח רבה מיניה בשמעתא. kehai lishna kama de'afillu halvahu assur kayma
lan kedemochach Rabbah mineih beshmata. So we פוסקין pasken even הלוהו. halvahu.
Even if you didn't say it at the time of the loan,
you bar סתם *stam* borrowed the money, later you cannot, you can't
offer this favor. Even if it wasn't in mind at the time
of the loan. So now תוספות *Tosafos* says והשתא קשיא דאדם שמלווה
לחבירו *vehashta kasha d'adom shemalveh l'chavero*. So you lent money to somebody.
וכי אסור לעשות לו שום טובה שבעולם *v'chi assur la'asos lo shum
tova she'ba'olam*? After I lent money to you, you can never do
me a favor now? And it's not only during the time you
haven't paid up, right? Maybe even a year later? It's a late
payment of what I, the fact that I lent you a loan.
So now it's forever אסור *assur* for you to do me a
favor? לא מבעיא דברים שאין רגילות להשאיל חינם כגון בית וסוס וכיוצא
בהם דאסור להשאיל למלווה *lo mibaya d'varim she'ein regilus l'hashil chinam k'gon
bayis v'sus v'chayotzei bahem d'assur l'hashil l'malveh*. אפילו הוא הווה *afillu hu
havei*. It would be one thing to say you can't do me
the types of favors you would normally not do כל כך *kol
kach*. Okay? דבלאו הכי היה משאיל *d'belav hachi haya mash'il*. אלא אפילו
דברים שרגיל להשאיל חינם לאחרים *ella afilu d'varim sheragil l'hashil chinam l'acherim*.
How about things that you normally would do favors to normal people
for? Your next door neighbor asks to borrow your rake, you lend
him your rake. Now the guy who lent you money asks to
borrow your rake, you can't lend it to him? שאינו רגילות ליטול
שכר מהם יהא אסור *she'einu regilus litol sachar mehem yei assur*? דר
בחצר חבירו לא קיימא לאגרא וגברא לא עביד למיסב דאסור *dar bachatzar
chaveiro lo kaima l'agra v'gavra lo avid l'meisav d'assur*? So what does
this mean? What's for this? Okay? If you can't let him live
in your field for free even though, then what are the types,
can you do no favors for him? Good question. So תוספות *Tosafos*
has two answers. ויש לומר דדווקא במילי דפרהסיא ואוושא טובא אסור הכא
כולי האי *v'yesh lomar d'davka bemilei d'parhesya v'avsha tuva assur hacha kulei
hai*, כגון דר בחצר *k'gon dar bachatzar*. So תוספות *Tosafos* no, the
reason it's forbidden here, normal favors, certainly favors that you would normally
do under other circumstances regardless of the loan would not be ריבית
*ribbis* like, except lending a field even if it would be a
normal type of a favor you would do. After you lent me
money, people walk by and see you living in my house after
knowing that you lent me money. Even if between us we know
I would normally have let you do it anyway, it looks like
ריבית *ribbis* to other people. So one aspect is it's particularly this
type of a favor which is very public. That's one answer. The
second answer is,
I'm going to skip, ועוד יש לומר *v'od yesh lomar*, if you
look like two lines down, beginning of a line, דדווקא לדבר שלא
מדעת חבירו אסור *davka l'davar shelo mida'as chaveiro assur*. הוא *hu* is
suggesting the favor. Okay? If you come ahead and you basically say
טוב *tov*, you let me money, I'm living in your house, okay,
which is like you let me money though, you're renting me your
car at a discount, or something like that. Okay? Those types of
things. Well דבלאו הכי *d'belav hachi*, that's different, that I wouldn't normally
do for other people. But I'm living in your house, if you
impose it on me, so then we say it's a type of
a ריבית *ribbis*. You feel you have that power, you let me
money, I owe you something. And therefore that's what makes it a
problem. But if I come and I freely do a favor for
you, and certainly a type of a favor that I would have
done otherwise regardless of the loan, that would not be a problem.
So a very important תוספות *Tosafos*. You let me money, even if
we did not structure it as part of the deal, it was
הלויהו *halveyhu* not הלווני *halveyini*. It could still be a problem of
me doing favors for you that would look like ריבית *ribbis*. But
what context doing a favor? Even a favor that's not worth a
cash dollar value, right? Even if you can't collect for it in
court, like we said, דר בחצר חבירו *dar bachatzar chaveiro*, it would
still be a problem. But תוספות *Tosafos* limits it to two cases
or to number one, it's only if it was, maybe it's certainly
a problem if you wouldn't normally have done such a favor for
that person. But if you would normally have done such a favor
for that person, it would only be a problem if either number
one, it's a public thing, so it looks to people like ריבית
*ribbis*, or number two, you're not the one doing the favor, he's
the one demanding the favor. If he's the one demanding the favor,
that's when there's a problem. Okay? So it's a nice way of
contextualizing what's going on in the גמרא *Gemara*. But the second case
of the משנה *Mishna*, when you're renting something at a discount, that
clearly is not a normal thing you would do. So that clearly
would be a ריבית *ribbis* problem. Okay. All right.